The 2011 Arab Spring
الربيع العربي في عام ٢٠٠١
captured the attention of the world.
جذب انتباه العالم.
It also captured the attention
وأيضاً جذب الأنتباه
of authoritarian governments in other countries,
الى الحكومات الإستبدادية في بعض الدول
who were worried that revolution would spread.
التي كانت قلقة من انتشار الثورة.
To respond, they ramped up surveillance
وللرد, لقد قاموا بتضخيم المراقبة
of activists, journalists and dissidents
للناشطين, الصحفيين, والمنشقّين
who they feared would inspire revolution
والذي كان الخوف منهم بأم يجتذبوا الثورة
in their own countries.
الى بلدانهم.
One prominent Bahraini activist,
أحد النشطاء البحرينيين,
who was arrested and tortured by his government,
والذي كان معتقل وعذّب من الحكومة
has said that the interrogators showed him
قال أن المحققين عرضوا عليه
transcripts of his telephone calls
نصوص لسجلات مكالماتة الهاتفية
and text messages.
والرسائل النصية.
Of course, it's no secret
بالطبع, هذا ليس سر
that governments are able to intercept telephone calls and text messages.
أن الحكومات قادرة على اعتراض المكالمات والرسائل النصية.
It's for that reason that many activists
ولهذا السبب العديد من الناشطيين
specifically avoid using the telephone.
بالذات يتحاشون استعمال الهاتف.
Instead, they use tools like Skype,
بدل ذلك, فهم يستخدمون ادوات مثل Skype
which they think are immune to interception.
والذي يعتقد انه محمي ضد الأعتراض.
They're wrong.
إنهم مخطئون.
There have now been over the last few years
خلال عده سنوات مضت ظهرت
an industry of companies
صناعة حديثة وشركات
who provide surveillance technology to governments,
تقدم خدمات وتقنيات مراقبة للحكومات,
specifically technology that allows those governments
وبالتحديد, تقنيات تتيح لتلك الحكومات
to hack into the computers
الى اختراق الأجهزة الشخصية
of surveillance targets.
للأهداف المراقبة.
Rather than intercepting the communications as they go over the wire,
بدلاً من اعتراض الأتصالات اثناء تنقلها كما هو معتاد ,
instead they now hack into your computer,
فهم الآن يقومون بإختراق الأجهزة الشخصية,
enable your webcam, enable your microphone,
وامكانية التسجيل من كاميرا العرض, من المايكروفون,
and steal documents from your computer.
ونسخ الستندات من الجهاز.
When the government of Egypt fell in 2011,
عندما سقطت الحكومة المصرية في عام ٢٠١١,
activists raided the office of the secret police,
نشطاء داهموا مكاتب عناصر الشرطة السرية
and among the many documents they found
وجزء من عدة مستندات عثروا عليها
was this document by the Gamma Corporation,
وجدوا هذا المستند من شركة جاما,
by Gamma International.
شركة جاما العالمية.
Gamma is a German company
شركة جاما هي شركة ألمانية
that manufactures surveillance software
وتقوم بتقديم برمجيات مراقبة
and sells it only to governments.
وبيعها فقط للحكومات.
It's important to note that most governments
يجب التنوية أن معظم الحكومات
don't really have the in-house capabilities
لا تملك قدرة محلية على
to develop this software.
تطوير تلك البرمجيات.
Smaller ones don't have the resources
لديهم برمجيات محدودة المصادر,
or the expertise,
وقلة خبراء
and so there's this market of Western companies
ولذلك, يوجد سوق الشركات الغربية
who are happy to supply them with the tools
والتي يسعدها تقديم تلك الأدوات
and techniques for a price.
والتقنيات مقابل مال.
Gamma is just one of these companies.
جاما هي إحدى تلك الشركات.
I should note also that Gamma never actually sold
ويجب التنوية أن جاما فعليا لم تبع
their software to the Egyptian government.
برمجياتها إلى الحكومة المصرية.
They'd sent them an invoice for a sale,
هم فقط ارسلوا فاتورة بقيمة العرض
but the Egyptians never bought it.
ولكن المصريون لم يقبلوا العرض.
Instead, apparently, the Egyptian government
بدل ذلك. كما يبدو, الحكومة المصرية
used a free demo version of Gamma's software.
استعملت اصدارات مجانية محدوده من برمجيات جاما.
(Laughter)
((ضحك الجمهور))
So this screenshot is from a sales video
وهذه الصورة من مقطع فيديو للمبيعات
that Gamma produced.
التي تقدمها جاما.
Really, they're just emphasizing
بالواقع, هم فقط يؤكدون
in a relatively slick presentation
من خلال عرض ماكر نسبياً
the fact that the police can sort of sit
حقيقة إمكانية ان رجال الشرطة يمكنهم
in an air-conditioned office
وفي مكاتب مكيفة
and remotely monitor someone
التحكم عن بعد في شاشة أحد ما
without them having any idea that it's going on.
بدون أن يعرف ذلك.
You know, your webcam light won't turn on.
كما تعرفون, أن إشارة تشغيل كاميرا العرض لن تعمل.
There's nothing to indicate that the microphone is enabled.
لا يوجد اي سبيل لإظهار أن المايكروفون يعمل.
This is the managing director of Gamma International.
هذا هو المدير العام لشركة جاما العالمية.
His name is Martin Muench.
اسمه مارتين مانتش.
There are many photos of Mr. Muench that exist.
هناك عدة صور شخصية له.
This is perhaps my favorite.
وهذه ربما المفضلة لدي.
I'm just going to zoom in a little bit onto his webcam.
وساقوم بالتقريب قليلاً الى كاميرا العرض خاصته.
You can see there's a little sticker
يمكنكم رؤية وجود لاصق.
that's placed over his camera.
تم وضعه لتغطية الكاميرا.
He knows what kind of surveillance is possible,
هو يعرف عن امكانيات المراقبة المتوفرة,
and so clearly he doesn't want it to be used
وبكل وضوح هو لا يرد أن تستعمل تلك التقنيات
against him.
ضدة شخصياً.
Muench has said that he intends
مانتش أقر بأنه تعمد
for his software to be used
بأن تستعمل برمجياته
to capture terrorists and locate pedophiles.
لالتقاط صور للأرهابيين والمتحرشين بالأطفال.
Of course, he's also acknowledged that once
وبالطبع, هو يعرف انه تلك البرمجيات
the software has been sold to governments,
تم بيعها للحكومات
he has no way of knowing how it can be used.
وبالتالي لا يعرف بالضبط كيف سيتم استعمال تلك البرمجيات..
Gamma's software has been located on servers
برمجيات ميونيخ تم تحديدها تواجدها على سيرفرات
in countries around the world,
في عدة دول حول العالم
many with really atrocious track records
والعديد منها لديها سجل شنيع
and human rights violations.
لانتهاكات حقوق الإنسان.
They really are selling their software around the world.
تلك البرمجيات منتشرة حول العالم.
Gamma is not the only company in the business.
جاما ليست الشركة الوحيدة في هذا النشاط.
As I said, it's a $5 billion industry.
وكما قلت, انه نشاط بقيمة ٥ مليارات دولار.
One of the other big guys in the industry
احدى أهم الشركات في هذا النشاط
is an Italian company called Hacking Team.
هي شركة ايطالية اسمها فريق القرصنة.
Now, Hacking Team has what is probably
حالياً, تلك الشركة لديها على الأرجح
the slickest presentation.
أكثر العروض مكراً.
The video they've produced is very sexy,
والفيديو الذي انتجوه مثير جداً
and so I'm going to play you a clip
وسأقوم ايضاً بعرض مقطع لكم
just so you can get a feel
فقط لتستشعروا
both for the capabilities of the software
امكانيات تلك البرمجيات
but also how it's marketed
ولتعرفوا أيضاُ كيف يتم تسويقها
to their government clients.
لعملائهم من الحكومات.
(Video) Narrator: You want to look through your target's eyes.
(مقطع فيديو) المعلق: تريد أن ترى من خلال عيون هدفك.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
You have to hack your target.
يجب ان تخترق هدفك.
["While your target is browsing the web, exchanging documents, receiving SMS, crossing the borders"]
" بينما هدفك يتصفح الانترنت, ويتبادل المستندات, يستقبل الرسايل, متجاوزاً الحدود"
You have to hit many different platforms.
يجب أن تهاجم عدة أنظمة.
["Windows, OS X, iOS, Android, Blackberry, Symbian, Linux"]
" نظام ويندوز, ماكنتوش, نظام iOS, اندرويد, بلاكبيري, سيمبيان, لينكس"
You have to overcome encryption
يجب عليك التغلب على التشفير
and capture relevant data.
والحصول على المعلومات.
[Skype &amp; encrypted calls, target location, messaging, relationships,
"سكايبي والمكالماات المشفرة, موقع الهدف, الرسائل, العلاقات الشخصية,
web browsing, audio &amp; video"]
تصفح الانترنت, الصوت والصورة"
Being stealth and untraceable.
تتسلل ولايمكن تعقبك.
["Immune to any protection system Hidden collection infrastructure"]
"محمياً ضد أي نظام ومتخفياً بمجموعة من البنى التحتية"
Deployed all over your country.
تنتشر في جميع أرجاء الدولة.
["Up to hundreds of thousands of targets Managed from a single spot"]
" مئات من آلاف الأهداف يتم التحكم فيها من مكان واحد"
Exactly what we do.
بالضبط هذا ما نفعله.
Christopher Soghoian: So, it would be funny if it wasn't true,
كريستوفر سوجويون: سيكون ذلك مضحكاً لو لم تكن حقيقة
but, in fact, Hacking Team's software
ولكن, بالواقع, برامج فريق القرصنة
is being sold to governments around the world.
يتم بيعها لحكومات حول العالم.
Last year we learned, for example,
العام الماضي تعلمنا, على سبيل المثال,
that it's been used to target Moroccan journalists by the Moroccan government.
انه تم استعمالها لتعقب صحفي مغربي بواسطة الحكومة المغربية.
Many, many countries it's been found in.
العديد, والعديد من الدول كانوا كذلك.
So, Hacking Team has also been actively courting
كما أن , فريق القرصنة قاموا بالمغازلة بشكل نشيط
the U.S. law enforcement market.
مع مكتب تطبيق القانون في أمريكا.
In the last year or so, the company
في العام الماضي او نحوه, الشركة
has opened a sales office in Maryland.
قامت بفتح مكتب مبيعات في ماريلاند.
The company has also hired a spokesperson.
الشركة قامت بتوظيف متحدث رسمي.
They've been attending
وقاموا بحضور
surveillance industry conferences
مؤتمرات في صناعة المراقبة
where law enforcement officials show up.
حيث كان يحضر مكتب تطبيق القانون.
They've spoken at the conferences.
وقد تحدثوا في تلك المؤتمرات.
What I thought was most fascinating was
وما أعتقد انه ألأكثر اذهالاً
they've actually paid for the coffee break
انه قاموا بتقديم القهوة في الاستراحة
at one of the law enforcement conferences
في إحدى مؤتمرات مكتب تطبيق القانون.
earlier this year.
مؤخراً هذه السنة.
I can't tell you for sure that Hacking Team
لا أستطيع تأكيد ان فريق القرصنة
has sold their technology in the United States,
قد باعوا تقنياتهم في الولايات المتحدة,
but what I can tell you that if they haven't sold it,
ولكن ما استطيع قوله هو أنهم ان لو يبيعوها,
it isn't because they haven't been trying hard.
ليس ذلك بأنهم لو يحاولوا جاهداً.
So as I said before,
وكما قلت قبل,
governments that don't really have the resources
حكومات ليست لديها المصادرة
to build their own tools will buy
لبناء أدواتهم سوق يشترون
off-the-shelf surveillance software,
من تنقيات المراقبة المتوفرة للاستعمال فوراً.
and so for that reason,
ولذلك السبب
you see that the government of, say, Tunisia,
ترى حكومات, لنقل, التونسية,
might use the same software as the government of Germany.
تستعمل نفس النظام المستعمل في ألمانيا.
They're all buying off-the-shelf stuff.
جميعهم يشترون التقنيات المتوفرة.
The Federal Bureau of Investigation in the United States
مكتب التحقيقات الفيدرالي في الولايات المتحدة
does have the budget to build their own surveillance technology,
يملك الميزانية لبناء تقنيات المراقبة
and so for several years, I've been trying
ولذك ولعدة سنوات, حاولت
to figure out if and how the FBI
لمعرفة اذا كان وكيف مكتب FBI
is hacking into the computers of surveillance targets.
يخترق أجهزة الأهداف المراقبة.
My friends at an organization called the Electronic Frontier Foundation --
صديقي في مؤسسة اسمها مؤسسة الحدود الإلكترونية
they're a civil society group —
وهم مجموعة مدنية
obtained hundreds of documents from the FBI
حصلوا على المئات من الملفات من FBI
detailing their next generation of surveillance technologies.
تفصل الجيل القادم من تقنية المراقبة.
Most of these documents were heavily redacted,
معظم هذه المستندات تم تنقيحها بشكل دقيق
but what you can see from the slides,
ولكن ما تستطيع رؤيته في هذا الشرائح
if I zoom in, is this term:
اذا قمت بالتقريب الى هذا المصطلح:
Remote Operations Unit.
وحده العمليات عن بعد.
Now, when I first looked into this,
الآن, عندما نظرت الى هذا لأول مرة
I'd never heard of this unit before.
لم أكن سمعت بهذه الوحدة من قبل.
I've been studying surveillance for more than six years.
لقد كنت أدرس تنقيات المراقبة من ٦ سنوات.
I'd never heard of it.
لم أسمع بهذا على الأطلاق.
And so I went online and I did some research,
ولهذا قمت ببعض البحث في الانترنت
and ultimately I hit the mother lode
وفي النهاية وصلت الى الوريد الأساسي
when I went to LinkedIn,
عندما فتحت موقع شركة LinkedIn
the social networking site for job seekers.
صفحة التواصل الإجتماعي المخصصة للباحثين عن عمل.
There were lots of former U.S. government contractors
هناك العديد من المقاولين السابقين للحكومة الأمريكية
who had at one point worked
والذي في فترة ما عملوا
for the Remote Operating Unit,
في وحدة التشغيل عن بعد,
and were describing in surprising detail on their CVs
والتي تم وصفها بشكل مفصل في سيرهم الذاتية.
what they had done in their former job.
وماالذي قاموا بمزاولته في تلك الوظائف.
(Laughter)
((ضحك))
So I took this information
ولذك قمت بجمع تلك المعلومات
and I gave it to a journalist that I know and trust at the Wall Street Journal,
واعطيتها لصحفية أثق فيها في صحيفه وول ستريبت
and she was able to contact several other
والتي استطاعت الوصول الى عدة
former law enforcement officials
ضباط سابقين في مكتب تطبيق القانون
who spoke on background and confirmed
والذين تحدثوا عن تاريخ وأقروا
that yes, in fact, the FBI has a dedicated team
ذلك, وبالفعل, مكتب FBI لديه فريق
that does nothing but hack into the computers
والذي مهمته فقط اختراق وقرصنة الحاسبات
of surveillance targets.
لأهداف المراقبة,
Like Gamma and Hacking Team,
وكما شركه جاما وفريق القرصنة,
the FBI also has the capability
FBI لديهم الامكانية
to remotely activate webcams, microphones,
وعن بعد لتنشيط كاميرات ومايكروفنات
steal documents, get web browsing information,
سرقة مستندات, والحصول على بيانات التصفح
the works.
إتمام العمل.
There's sort of a big problem
هناك عدة مشاكل كبيرة
with governments going into hacking,
مع الحكومات الراغبة في القرصنة
and that's that terrorists, pedophiles,
وذلك أن الأرهابيين والمتحرشين
drug dealers, journalists and human rights activists
مروجي المخدرات, الصحفيين ونشطاء حقوق الإنسان
all use the same kinds of computers.
يستعملون نفس أجهزه الكمبيوتر.
There's no drug dealer phone
لا يوجد هاتف مخصص لمروج مخدرات
and there's no journalist laptop.
او حاسب محمول مخصص لصحفي.
We all use the same technology,
جميعنا نستعمل التقنية ذاتها
and what that means then is that for governments
ومايعني ذلك أن الحكومات
to have the capability to hack into the computers
ليكون لديها القدرة على اختراق تلك الأجهزة
of the real bad guys,
لأولئك الأشرار
they also have to have the capability
يجب أن يتملكوا الأمكانية
to hack into our devices too.
لاختراق أجهزتنا ايضاً.
So governments around the world
لذا الحكومات حول العالم
have been embracing this technology.
قاموا بحصر هذه التقنية.
They've been embracing hacking
لقد قاموا بحصر الاختراق والقرصنة
as a law enforcement technique,
كوسيلة لتطبيق القانون
but without any real debate.
ولكن بدون أي مناقشات حقيقىه.
In the United States, where I live,
في الولايات المتحدة, حيث أعيش
there have been no congressional hearings.
لم يكن هناك تصريح لمجلس الشبوخ.
There's no law that's been passed
لا يوجد قانون تم إقراره
specifically authorizing this technique,
يعطي الصلاحية لتلك التقنية بالتحديد
and because of its power and potential for abuse,
وبسبب قوة وامكانية إساءة استعمالها
it's vital that we have an informed public debate.
فإنة واجب أن نناقش ذلك مع الشعب.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلاً
(Applause)
((تصفيق))